All right, welcome back to the lam rim.
I'd like to start right off with this photograph you see here
of a lady and
she's rushing to work in her car and
she's looking at her watch.
That's exactly how I looked about a half an hour ago.
I live about 45 minutes away from the college here.
and I rushed to get into my car.
I'm late,
Tim and Seiji, are
getting irritated at me and I'm rushing.
And I jump in the car.
Okay, if I just push it I can make it.
I start the car and I'm racing down the road.
I get about half way here, and
I realized I forgot my computer.
I can't do the video.
I'll have to go back to my house.
And then it's just, forget it!
Tim's gonna give me that pleasant smile that says, you're unbelievably late.
That's how you feel stupid, when you rush and
then you you get your car to go someplace.
Then you realize you forgot something important.
And then the whole rushing is useless
and you got to go back to get what you forgot and come back again.
So the theme today is called 'rushing to work'.
or 'doing things twice'.
In American English, we call it double work.
Having to do double work.
What's that mean double work? Well, let's let's read this.
We're gonna read a little poem. It's by a great master named Aryasura.
I got to think he lived around the time of...
his book was translated into Chinese...
we know the date,  434 AD
it was translated to Chinese.
He must be, I guess, he's around the time of Nagarjuna.
Maybe almost 2000 years ago and he wrote this poem.
This poem is from a short book on the perfection of wisdom.
A short book about the pen.
And it says ,'JIG RTEN DON SGRUB TSUL LA MTHU MED PA'I
THEG PA GNYIS PO GTAN DU SPANG BYAS SHING
THUB RGYAL THEG PA SNYING RJES BSTAN PA LA
GZHAN PHAN RO GCIG RANG BZHIN DE DAG 'JUG
okay, ,'JIG RTEN DON SGRUB TSUL LA MTHU MED PA'I,
'JIG RTEN DON SGRUB is a beautiful expression.
DON SGRUB by itself... Okay for $50.00
Sanskrit?
40, 30, 20, 10...
siddhartha
Yeah siddhartha .....
It means to achieve the goals. So 'JIG RTEN DON SGRUB
The name of the Buddha when he was a prince is Siddhartha,
and it means to do what you have to do for other people.
'JIG RTEN means for other people.
so, 'JIG RTEN DON SGRUB....
TSUL means this special system where you have in mind all these beings,
that you saw one by one, the countless beings that you saw one by one.
You're thinking about them.
You're thinking about how to take care of them.
There are some people LA MTHU MED PA'I,
they get distracted by THEG PA GNYIS PO;
the idea that there's two different ways to approach your spiritual life.
It might be the case, that if you've been sitting through this lam rim for years,
then you're kind of getting used to the idea
that there are basically two separate tracks.
We say three, but the lower two are together.
You can think, well I could...
...go for the big one,
I could try to reach bodhichitta.
I could try to have this experience that Geshe-la has been talking about.
He keeps talking about it.
I don't know why he keeps talking about it, but he seems to think that such a thing is possible.
So, I could go that high way,
and I could try to do something
that would help every single being in the universe.
And kind of, I would have to be taking it on faith.
I would have to be thinking,
Well, it is possible to meet everybody in the universe.
It is possible to promise each of them one by one that I will work for you.
I would have to kind of take it on faith from Geshe-la and these great books.
So that's one way you could go.
Or you can say, that sounds great,
that certainly sounds amazing but let me just start where I am.
Let me do my morning meditations and try to be patient with my husband in the kitchen.
Let me start where people start.
Maybe I'll try to get to that other thing later.
I'll try I'll try to get to that other thing later, where you try to see all the beings in the universe.
It sounds a little bit over-the-top right now.
Even to choose understanding the husband,
and understanding the pen ... over
trying to have this experience
where you see every living being in the universe.
It's called wasted effort or double effort in English.
It means you're gonna have to come back later and do it anyway.
It's like taking off fast from your house in your car
and then you have to turn around and go back
to pick up something you forgot because you took off too fast.
What he is saying here is MTHU MED PA'I,,THEG PA GNYIS PO
If you think about it,
all the paths, all the approaches, you can think of other than
trying to see every living being and do things for them,
are actually MTHU MED PA.
MTHU MED PA means fruitless.
They won't get you anywhere. You're gonna have to go back and start over again anyway.
So it's a very powerful criticism.
He's almost criticizing seeing emptiness directly.
We're going to get into that kind of a feeling here and it's dangerous territory.
Isn't seeing emptiness directly the greatest thing you can do?
Why is he talking about it.... in a way, how could that be pointless MTHU MED PA.
GTAN DU SPANG BYAS SHING,
he says, give up this idea
that you could have an option to start with lower meditations or lower goals.
You have to start from the top.
You have to start from trying to trigger this experience of every living being.
Because if you do it that way, then you won't have to go back and start over again.
You won't have to go back to your house and get the thing you forgot and come back again.
You're wasting time. Okay.
SPANG BYAS give up this idea that you have an option.
Of course, you have to see emptiness directly. Of course, you have to understand the pen.
But now that we've reached a higher capacity person section,
we can say for the first time in 10 years,
that it's a very high priority to have this experience,
this direct experience of helping or speaking to every living being.
You can imagine if you have had that experience,
your whole life has changed,
your whole life changes.
Nothing's the same anymore and all of your priorities,
all of your hopes, dreams,
all of your activities,
everything is completely different from other people.
It's important to try to have this experience.
We're going to talk about it a lot for the rest of this retreat.
THEG PA SNYING PO
THEG PA SNYING PO RJES BSTAN PA LA
THUB RGYAL THEG PA SNYING RJES BSTAN PA LA
GZHAN PHAN RO GCIG RANG BZHIN DE DAG 'JUG
Give up this idea that
you should focus on anything else
THUB RGYAL THEG PA SNYING RJES BSTAN PA LA
Concentrate on the one way THEG PA
that the Buddha taught, that's based on SNYING RJES,
taking care of other people.
Trying to repeat that experience that we keep talking about;
that you could meet
every living being that there is.
and that would be a unique experience in your life,
that few minutes, that 15-20 minutes or 1/2 hour,
that would define your whole life.
And all of your life would change, all of your priorities would change.
And you'd be on the way to true happiness and and the purpose of why you were born.
GZHAN PHAN RO GCIG RANG BZHIN DE DAG 'JUG
Jump into the ocean of the single song.
And it means GZHAN PHAN.
GZHAN PHAN means taking care of other people.
Working for the good of countless living beings
that you have met directly one by one.
And wouldn't that be great in our retreat
if one or two people or 10 people had this experience.
Wouldn't that be something if some people,
actually met all the beings in in the universe
during a half hour or something.
Wouldn't that be beautiful?
CES DANG
I went and checked the quotation and it's correct.
And there's nothing new to say about it.
Then he quotes Geshe Potowa,
who is one of the early kadampa geshes from about almost exactly a thousand years ago.
He says... and these kadampa kind of guys ...they were first-generation.
They're kind of like the hippies who first went to India in my generation.
They started out pretty strange people,
like really weird people in their country and and
they were like the kind of the crazy hippies
who went to India and
brought back these ideas.
I kind of feel drawn to them and I feel proud of them, but they didn't grow up in monasteries.
They were people who had courage
to work in a different way
then their whole culture up to that time.
They were Tibetans who wanted to learn these things.
They were the first generation.
And I think we all kind of count as first generation and to me it's very, very exciting.
I almost prefer that we didn't grow up in a Buddhist country.
We are learning it because we have courage and we want to learn it and I almost prefer that.
He said, Geshe Potowa said...
by the way, geshe in those days was not a monastery degree.
Geshe just meant in those days
a kadampa teacher, a kadampa master.
Mostly they were laypeople and there were family people.
RAB BRGAL GCIG LA BRDZE BCANG GNYIS MIN
DANG PO NYID NAS THEG CHEN LAM 'JUG
He said, in Tibet
there are countless streams, and if you go anywhere
you're gonna have to cross these streams.
It's a big thing in Tibet.
It's like brushing your teeth in America or something.
You're gonna be doing it many times every day.
You're gonna be riding a horse through the shallow part of a stream,
because Tibet is the Himalayan mountains
where all the great rivers of Asia start.
The Yangtze, the Mekong, the Ganges,
Brahmaputra, all the great rivers of Asia start in Tibet.
So you're always crossing little streams that become great rivers.
He says,
don't don't be dumb and cross the stream at the wrong place
so you have to cross it again in ten minutes
because if there's a circle, or there's a curve or something.
Be smart, watch your map, you don't have to cross the same stream twice.
What that means is
go straight for the experience of meeting every living being and then that's it. You're done.
You don't have to go back to it.
It's not like you forgot something at home and you have to turn around and drive back.
You can be more efficient. Okay.
DANG PO NYID NAS THEG CHEN LAM 'JUG
From the very beginning
You should get into this mahayana, okay.
Mahayana means exactly that; you have this experience of meeting every living being.
The mahayana is not a system, mahayana is not a group of books.
Mahayana is meeting every living being directly and making a commitment to them.
By the way, if you're interested his poetry is very unusual, it's an even number of syllables.
It's eight syllables.
Usually, it's da da da da da da da
Okay, and here is DANG PO NYID NAS THEG CHEN LAM 'JUG
and it feels strange in Tibetan.
It feels unique, okay.
CES PA LTAR CHU GCIG LA BRGAL THENGS GNYIS BYED DGOS BYUNG BA LTAR 'GYUR LA
You don't want to have to cross the same river twice and pull up your clothes twice.
That's what it says, people in Tibet wore mostly robes
even lay people wore big heavy coats.
It would be silly to have to you pull up your pants twice to cross the same river.
BYUNG BA LTAR 'GYUR LA.
DER MA ZAD DGRA BCOM PA DE DAG ZHI BDE'I DBYINGS LA SNYOMS PAR
ZHUGS PA NA
BDE BA'I NYAMS BSAM GYIS MI KHYAB PA YOD PAS
Then he jumps topic.
By the way, if you ever learn Tibetan, this book is unbelievable. This book is extraordinary.
This book is surely the greatest Tibetan book ever written in Tibetan.
And that was all by Trijang Rinpoche,
my teacher's teacher,
who wrote the book, who wrote the teaching down.
And then you have to think that he spent years of his life making it perfect.
The spelling is perfect. These sentences are perfect. The meaning is perfect. Okay
I have never found a mistake in the content of this book
DER MA ZAD DGRA BCOM PA DE DAG ZHI
He jumps suddenly. He jumps why?
He says arhats, lets talk about arhats.
Let's talk about people who reached nirvana.
ZHI BDE'I DBYINGS LA SNYOMS PAR ZHUGS
By the way, he's talking about lower arhats
people who've reached a lower nirvana.
If you've reached a higher nirvana that's already Buddhahood.
So there's not much reason to talk about it.
Here he says,
arhats who  managed to reach nirvana, lower nirvana.
They just cut all their negative emotions.
They are capable of sitting here on this couch
for a million years
in some kind of pure clean happiness
without any kind of trouble
or doubts or problems.
DE DAG ZHI BDE'I DBYINGS
ZHI BDE'I DBYINGS means
the realm of peace and happiness.
They can sit there  for a million years.
BDE BA'I NYAMS BSAM GYIS MI KHYAB PA
BSAM GYIS MI KHYAB PA means  unbelievable.
It's hard for us to imagine
the pleasure of being a lower arhat.
It's not like some kind of drugged out,
dumb meditation or something.
It's bright. It's aware. It's perfect. It's with the total understanding of emptiness and
they live there for millions of years in that state, okay.
Let's go to the next paragraph;
DE LAS SLAR MI LDANG SNYAM NAS DE LA BSKAL PA MANG PO'I BAR MNYAM PAR BZHAG
Then of course, they think to themselves;
"Well, I think I'll just hang out here, there is no reason to get up now".
SLAR MI LDANG means they don't want to get back up, they just sit there.
DE ... LDANG ... NAS DE LA BSKAL PA MANG PO'I for many millions of years.
MNYAM PAR BZHAG  in meditation.
DE'I YUN RING THUNG DMYAL BA NA GNAS PA 'GA' ZHIG
Now, very interesting comparison.                                   You got to keep in mind the comparison.
Over here, there's a person who reached nirvana.
Over here is a person who reached Nirvana and they're hanging out in this beautiful personal space.
Over here Is a person who went to the hells, they went to the hell realms,
and they spent a long long time there.
They burnt off that negative karma in the hell realms.
They burnt off that negative karma and then they rose back up to the human realm.
So they they've dropped to the hell realms, they spent tens of thousands of years there,
then DAL 'BYOR THOB
they got back a human life of leisure and fortune.
They came back to a human life of leisure and fortune, all the necessities of a human life.
THOB CING THEG CHEN GYI LAM LA ZHUGS
They found a Mahayana teacher,
and that teacher taught them
how to have that experience of countless living beings.
They got 'TSANG RGYA THUB PA
They got enlightened.
They actually worked hard and got enlightened
TZAM DU SDOD
So on the one hand,
here's this guy who reached a personal nirvana and he's hanging out there.
And on the other hand,
here's this guy who was bad in this life and he dropped to the hell realms
and he spent a hundreds of thousands of years there.
He fought his way back up to a human life
and in that human life
he entered the mahayana and he became a bodhisattva.
Which is better?
And which is faster? Which takes less time? Which is more efficient?
No. Going to hell, okay!
Ii's more efficient, it's really weird.
It's a very weird, extremely weird statement.
I'll say it again.
Here's a guy,
let's say he did the lion's dance correctly and he got to a place of personal nirvana.
He's hanging out there for millions of years, but he cannot become a Buddha.
He's just an arhat, a personal happy space.
Here's this other guy.
He hurt people, he killed people, he shot people.
He went to the hell realms and he worked it off.
He fought his way back up to human life. He'd study, study, study, and he became a Buddha.
Which would you rather be?
Pabongka says, the second one. It's very cool. It' very strange.
Then go to hell.  I guess he means it literally!
SANGS RGYAS KYI GO 'PHANG THOB PA LA 'GYANGS SHIN TU CHE BAS NA THEG CHEN RIGS CAN THEG DMAN GYI LAM DU ZHUGS TE DGRA BCOM THOB PA LAS
People in the know,
people who really understand the way things are,
They do their best to stay out of a personal nirvana.
They don't try to go there because it's so delicious you are going to spend millions of years there.
Then you're still gonna have to cross the river again.
You're still gonna have to go back and pick up bodhichitta and come back again.
THEG DMAN GYI LAM DU ZHUGS TE DGRA BCOM THOB PA LAS, THEG CHEN GYI CHOS THOS NAS BAG CHAGS BZHAG
This is really cool. Better than that, we should go to a teaching,
we should hear about this experience of
promising to help every living being.
We should plant that seed in our mind
then we should get a very serious wrong view,
destroy all the good karma we have.
Then get born in the hells, and fight our way back to a human life.
Then in that life, that seed opens
from lifetimes ago where I heard a mahayana teaching.
I heard somebody say you could meet every living being
and then that old seed ripens after
thousands of years in the hell.
'TSANG RGYA BAR MYUR that would be faster, 'TSANG RGYA BAR MYUR BA that would be faster.
DE BZANG BA, and so that would be better.
That would be a better route to take, to the hell realms,
then to sit in a personal nirvana and waste more time.
That's kind of an extraordinary statement.
I got a picture here...
I enjoy looking up these pictures. I got my credit card bill the other day,  apparently I'm enjoying it too much!
I am not complaining, I'm just saying I was like 'what the heck, why is it so high?' Then I realized that it was all these lam rim pictures.
So anyway,
you got this picture of a man showing the... this guy...
okay, now listen what's going on here?
You think it's just a plain old picture but it's not.
This is a very deep Buddhist picture. It took me many... I had to go to ACIP,
dig around in the ancient books and I found this picture.
Okay, just kidding.
This lady asked the guy,
"How do I get the Rimrock?" And the guy said to her,
"Well, I can tell you it's Highway 17,
but it's blocked up. They had an accident, it is going to take you a long time to get there.
You should take the long way around because you'll get there faster."
"There's a traffic accident and I'm telling you that the road you want is faster usually but tonight there was an accident."
"I suggest you you take the detour" and she says 'No'.
"I don't want to, I don't trust you. Just tell me where's Highway 17."
"I don't believe you that is slower".
"I'm not gonna take this detour that you're talking about".
Then if he's a Buddha, he says, "Oh, okay. I suggested Highway 17 was blocked up tonight,
and I suggested you take the long way around because it would be faster tonight,
but you don't trust me, you want to take Highway 17.
Go, take this exit and you'll be on Highway 17. Everything will be good."
But he's lying.
And he lies to her.
Very funny. This is what we're gonna be talking about. I'll say it again.
Highway 17 is the best way to get to Rimrock from Phoenix.
This lady is asking this man, how do I get the Highway 17?
This man knows that Highway 17 is slower tonight.
He tells her, don't take Highway 17, I'll show you a slower route.
'No, I don't want to slower route'.
And he says listen, it is a slower route
but you're going to get there faster because tonight Highway 17 is blocked.
And she says, 'I don't trust you.
just tell me where Highway 17 is'.
He says, 'Take this exit'.
But he's telling her to take the exit for the long way.
Because he loves her.
He wants to help her.
It's kind of funny. It's a funny example, but it's perfect. Trust me. Here we go...
Here's the text; DPER NA SNGON NYAN THOS 'OD SRUNG GIS THEG DMAN GYI CHOS BSTAN NA DGRA BCOM PA 'THOB RGYU'I DGE SLONG DRUG CU LA
'JAM DPAL DBYANGS KYIS SNGON DU PHEBS TE THEG CHEN GYI CHOS BSTAN PAS
So in days gone by,
there was a lower arhat, named Kashyapa, there's many Kashyapas.
THEG DMAN GYI CHOS BSTAN NA
He was teaching a lower way hinayana,
DGRA BCOM PA 'THOB RGYU'I DGE SLONG DRUG CU
There were 60 guys who are about to attain nirvana,
on a lower track.
60 people were ready, about to attain nirvana on a lower track,
because this great hinayana teacher was teaching them how to do it.
And they were just about to hit it.
Because they were just about to hit lower nirvana,
Manjushri emanated there.
The Buddha of wisdom emanated there and he purposely taught them
this idea of meeting all living beings directly,
and having a conversation with them and telling them 'I'll take care of you'.
CHOS BSTAN PAS BLOR MA CHUD
It didn't fit them.
Now get this, here is a Buddha,
an enlightened being who can read a person's mind and he gives them the wrong teaching!
Purposely he teaches them mahayana.
These guys are about to reach hinayana nirvana,
Manjushri breaks in and
teaches them Higher Way.
What happens?
BLOR MA CHUD PAR LOG LTA BYAS what's LOG LTA BYAS for $50?
Yeah, 50 bucks for him remind me
These guys said to Manjushri, 'you're an asshole."
We're about to achieve nirvana and he is talking crazy.
We got to go meet every living being, go to hell. LOG LTA BYAS
Now it's kind of weird because Manjushri
knew they're gonna say that and he still said what he said. Why?
It's the guy showing the lady where to go.
He wants them to go to hell.
Because it'll be faster.
It's amazing, it's incredible!
He says something that he knows doesn't fit them,
because he wants them to disrespect a Buddha and
instead of going to lower nirvana, they will go to hell.
But with a seed in their mind for having heard about the mahayana.
Cool, it's really weird. This is really weird.
I mean, following this kind of behavior could be dangerous if we don't see the future.
I think we should kind of be careful with this kind of approach. Okay.
THEG CHEN GYI CHOS BSTAN PAS BLOR MA CHUD PAR LOG LTA BYAS TE, DMYAL BAR SKYES PA
They went to hell.
'OD SRUNG GIS STON PA LA ZHUS PA NA
Then that Hinayana teacher, KASHYAPA got upset and
went to the Buddha to issue a complaint about Manjushri.
He said, "I was teaching these 60 people who were ready to reach nirvana,
this guy comes up and pisses them off.
They get mad at him. They break their meditation. They go to the hell realms.
Is this guy your student?
Shakyamuni says, 'Yeah, that's my student'.
'JAM DBYANGS KYIS THABS MKHAS
What's THABS MKHAS  for $50?
THABS MKHAS, Manjushri's just doing THABS MKHAS,
Yeah, so now I owe him 100. Okay
Shakyamuni says to Kashabya, which is not the Buddha Kashabya, that's another Kashabya.
He says, "listen Manjushri is trying to
get them to go to hell".
Then the guy says, "What"! He says, 'yeah'.
it's called ....there's anew word for it...
Unexpected strategy. What did you call it Seiji in your business talk?
.....
Disruptive innovation - perfect.
Oh, Manjushri is just doing disruptive innovation.
What do you mean disruptive innovation?
He wants them to go to hell because it would be faster.
Then crossing the stream twice. Okay. All right, very interesting.
Very interesting ....by the way, in the lamrim
we're about to reach a section where Pabongka Rinpoche says,
'look people say lam rim is for kids, but lam rim is straight tantra, for sure.
'JAM DBYANGS KYIS THABS MKHAS BSTAN PA DE NYID LEGS PAR GSUNGS.
LEGS PAR GSUNGS he says, Manjushri
Perfect approach, perfect strategy LEGS PAR...LEGS SO
We're almost done. Hang in there.
NYAN RANG DGRA BCOM RNAMS ZHI MTHAR MNYAM GZHAG SKABS SANGS RGYAS KYIS BSKUL TE THEG CHEN LA BTZUD NA'ANG
SNGAR ZHI BDE'I RO LA MNYAM PAR BZHAG PA LA GOMS CHES PAS
so NYAN RANG DGRA BCOM RNAMS There are lower arhats in nirvana.
MNYAM GZHAG SKABS they go into these deep states of personal nirvana.
There's a famous thing I taught you in the ACI courses, what happens at that point?
Yeah, you've been there for like a million years and you get a tap on the shoulder.
Buddha arranges it.
Buddha says, 'hey, you're not done yet. Get up. You still got to go back and
cross the stream again. Turn around, go back home, get the thing you forgot.
He wakes them up.
Somebody should write a play about it or something, it should be some guy meditating and
some guy comes up and puts French fries in front of his nose, and he says 'get up'.
BSKUL TE THEG CHEN LA BTZUD NA'ANG
And then Buddha got them to enter the mahayana but
SNGAR ZHI BDE'I RO LA MNYAM PAR BZHAG PA LA GOMS CHES PAS
They will still have propensities,
karmic propensities in their mind
for this kind of spaced out nirvana.
And those are dangerous. ..
So Buddha didn't choose...
Manjushri didn't choose to let them
reach nirvana and then go wake them up halfway through.
Because then they would still have bad seeds in their mind.
They would still be attracted to that lower nirvana. So he sent them to hell.
It's very interesting
THEG CHEN LA BTZUD NA'ANG......SEMS BSKYED SOGS RGYUD LA BSKYED PAR MI BRTZON
and then they wouldn't be attracted to having this meeting with all living beings.
Or BRTZON KYANG RANG SDUG BSNGAL LAS GROL BAS SNYING RJE SOGS SKYE DKA'
These guys who are sitting in a personal nirvana,
it's hard for them to get SNYING RJE
karuna
It's compassion SKYE DKA' it's hard for them. They can't empathize with normal people.
They can't think of how hard their lives are, their life is too pleasant.
The best bodhisattva is one who has a lot of personal problems and
then they can be a really good bodhisattva.
If you're taking this retreat and you have a lot of personal problems
and you think I'm not a very good Buddhist or I couldn't help other people very much...
Right here, the Buddha says 'you're perfect for a bodhisattva.
People who've had a lot of trouble in their life, people who have failed over and over
you are the best people to teach the bodhisattva teachings
because you've been there.
The job of a bodhisattva is to love other people who are in trouble
And you can't really love them if you don't know that trouble, okay?
Okay, so all of you who are taking this retreat, you know, and you've been not such a perfect person in your life
you're are perfect candidates for bodhisattva and
we'll talk more about it in the next episode. Thank you